The President: Good
afternoon, everybody.
Yesterday was
a historic day.
The comprehensive, long-term
deal that we achieved with
our allies and partners to
prevent Iran from obtaining
a nuclear weapon represents
a powerful display of
American leadership
and diplomacy.
It shows what we can
accomplish when we lead from
a position of strength and a
position of principle, when
we unite the international
community around a shared
vision, and we resolve to
solve problems peacefully.
As I said yesterday, it's
important for the American
people and Congress to get a
full opportunity to review
this deal.
That process is
now underway.
I've already reached out to
leaders in Congress on both
sides of the aisle.
My national security team
has begun offering
extensive briefings.
I expect the debate to be
robust -- and that's
how it should be.
This is an important issue.
Our national security
policies are stronger and
more effective when they are
subject to the scrutiny and
transparency that
democracy demands.
And as I said yesterday, the
details of this deal matter
very much.
That's why our team worked
so hard for so long to get
the details right.
At the same time, as this
debate unfolds, I hope we
don't lose sight of the
larger picture -- the
opportunity that this
agreement represents.
As we go forward, it's
important for everybody to
remember the alternative and
the fundamental choice that
this moment represents.
With this deal, we cut off
every single one of Iran's
pathways to a nuclear
program -- a nuclear weapons
program, and Iran's nuclear
program will be under severe
limits for many years.
Without a deal, those
pathways remain open; there
would be no limits on Iran's
nuclear program, and Iran
could move closer
to a nuclear bomb.
With this deal, we
gain unprecedented,
around-the-clock monitoring
of Iran's key nuclear
facilities and the most
comprehensive and intrusive
inspection and verification
regime ever negotiated.
Without a deal, those
inspections go away, and we
lose the ability to closely
monitor Iran's program and
detect any covert
nuclear weapons program.
With this deal, if Iran
violates its commitments,
there will be real
consequences.
Nuclear-related sanctions
that have helped to cripple
the Iranian economy will
snap back into place.
Without a deal, the
international sanctions
regime will unravel,
with little ability
to re-impose them.
With this deal, we have the
possibility of peacefully
resolving a major threat to
regional and international
security.
Without a deal, we risk even
more war in the Middle East,
and other countries in the
region would feel compelled
to pursue their own nuclear
programs, threatening a
nuclear arms race in the
most volatile region
in the world.
As I said yesterday, even
with this deal, we will
continue to have profound
differences with Iran -- its
support for terrorism and
its use of proxies to
destabilize parts
of the Middle East.
Therefore, the multilateral
arms embargo on Iran will
remain in place for an
additional five years, and
restrictions on ballistic
missile technology will
remain for eight years.
In addition, the United
States will maintain our own
sanctions related to Iran's
support for terrorism, its
ballistic missile program,
and its human rights
violations.
And we'll continue our
unprecedented security
cooperation with Israel
and continue to deepen our
partnerships with
the Gulf States.
But the bottom line is this:
This nuclear deal meets the
national security interests
of the United States
and our allies.
It prevents the most serious
threat -- Iran obtaining a
nuclear weapon, which would
only make the other problems
that Iran may
cause even worse.
That's why this deal makes
our country, and the world,
safer and more secure.
It's why the alternative --
no limits on Iran's nuclear
program, no inspections,
an Iran that's closer to a
nuclear weapon, the risk of
a regional nuclear arms race
and a greater risk of
war -- all that would
endanger our security.
That's the choice
that we face.
If we don't choose wisely, I
believe future generations
will judge us harshly
for letting this moment
slip away.
And no one suggests that
this deal resolves all the
threats that Iran poses to
its neighbors or the world.
Moreover, realizing the
promise of this deal will
require many years
of implementation
and hard work.
It will require
vigilance and execution.
But this deal is our best
means of assuring that Iran
does not get a
nuclear weapon.
And, from the start, that
has been my number-one
priority, our
number-one priority.
We've got a historic chance
to pursue a safer and more
secure world -- an
opportunity that may not
come again in our lifetimes.
As President and as
Commander-in-Chief, I am
determined to seize
that opportunity.
So with that, I'm going
to take some questions.
And let me see who I'm
starting off with.
Here you go.
I got it.
(laughter)
Andrew Beatty, AFP.
The Press: Thank
you, Mr. President.
Yesterday, you said the deal
offered a chance at a new
direction in
relations with Iran.
What steps will you take to
enable a more moderate Iran?
And does this deal allow you
to more forcefully counter
Iran's destabilizing actions
in the region quite aside
from the nuclear question?
Thank you.
The President: Andrew, if
you don't mind, just because
I suspect that there's
going to be a common set of
questions that are touched
on -- I promise I will get
to your question, but I
want to start off just by
stepping back and reminding
folks of what is at stake
here.
And I already did in my
opening statement, but I
just want to reiterate it
because I've heard already
some of the objections
to the deal.
The starting premise of our
strategy with respect to
Iran has been that it would
be a grave threat to the
United States and to our
allies if they obtained a
nuclear weapon.
And so everything that we've
done over the last six and a
half years has been designed
to make sure that we address
that number-one priority.
That's what the sanctions
regime was all about.
That's how we were able to
mobilize the international
community, including some
folks that we are not
particularly close to, to
abide by these sanctions.
That's how these crippling
sanctions came about, was
because we were able to gain
global consensus that Iran
having a nuclear weapon
would be a problem for
everybody.
That's the reason that
Iran's accounts got frozen
and they were not able to
get money for the oil sales
that they've made.
That's the reason that they
had problems operating with
respect to international
commerce -- because we built
that international consensus
around this very specific,
narrow, but profound issue
-- the possibility of Iran
getting a nuclear weapon.
And, by the way, that was
not simply my priority.
If you look back at all the
debates that have taken
place over the last five,
six years, this has been a
Democratic priority, this
has been a Republican
priority, this has been
Prime Minister Netanyahu's
priority.
It's been our Gulf allies'
priority -- is making sure
Iran does not get
a nuclear weapon.
The deal negotiated by John
Kerry, Wendy Sherman, Ernie
Moniz, our allies, our
partners, the P5+1
achieves that goal.
It achieves our top priority
-- making sure that Iran
does not get a
nuclear weapon.
But we have always
recognized that even if Iran
doesn't get a nuclear
weapon, Iran still poses
challenges to our interests
and our values, both in the
region and around the world.
So when this deal gets
implemented, we know that we
will have dismantled the
immediate concerns around
Iran's nuclear program.
We will have brought their
stockpiles down to 98
percent.
We will have significantly
reduced the number of
centrifuges that
they operate.
We will have installed an
unprecedented inspections
regime, and that will remain
in place not just for 10
years but, for example,
on the stockpiles, will
continue to 15 years.
Iran will have pledged to
the international community
that it will not develop a
nuclear weapon and now will
be subject to an Additional
Protocol, a more vigorous
inspection and monitoring
regime that lasts in
perpetuity.
We will have disabled a
facility like Arak, the Arak
facility, from allowing Iran
to develop plutonium that
could be used for a bomb.
We will have greatly reduced
the stockpile of uranium
that's enriched.
And we will have put in
place inspections along the
entire supply chain so that
if uranium was diverted into
a covert program
we would catch it.
So I can say with confidence
but, more importantly,
nuclear experts can say with
confidence that Iran will
not be in a position to
develop a nuclear bomb.
We will have met our
number-one priority.
Now, we'll still have
problems with Iran's
sponsorship of terrorism;
its funding of proxies like
Hezbollah that threaten
Israel and threaten the
region; the destabilizing
activities that they're
engaging in, including
in places like Yemen.
And my hope is that building
on this deal we can continue
to have conversations with
Iran that incentivize them
to behave differently in
the region, to be less
aggressive, less hostile,
more cooperative, to operate
the way we expect nations in
the international community
to behave.
But we're not
counting on it.
So this deal is not
contingent on Iran changing
its behavior.
It's not contingent on Iran
suddenly operating like a
liberal democracy.
It solves one particular
problem, which is making
sure they don't have a bomb.
And the point I've
repeatedly made -- and is, I
believe, hard to dispute --
is that it will be a lot
easier for us to check
Iran's nefarious activities,
to push back against the
other areas where they
operate contrary to our
interests or our allies'
interests, if they
don't have a bomb.
And so will they
change their behavior?
Will we seek to gain more
cooperation from them in
resolving issues like Syria,
or what's happening in Iraq,
to stop encouraging
Houthis in Yemen?
We'll continue to
engage with them.
Although, keep in mind that
unlike the Cuba situation,
we're not normalizing
diplomatic relations here.
So the contacts will
continue to be limited.
But will we try to encourage
them to take a more
constructive path?
Of course.
But we're not betting on it.
And in fact, having resolved
the nuclear issue, we will
be in a stronger position to
work with Israel, work with
the Gulf countries, work
with our other partners,
work with the Europeans to
bring additional pressure to
bear on Iran around those
issues that remain of
concern.
But the argument that I've
been already hearing -- and
this was foreshadowed
even before the deal was
announced -- that because
this deal does not solve all
those other problems, that
that's an argument for
rejecting this
deal, defies logic.
It makes no sense.
And it loses sight of what
was our original number-one
priority, which is making
sure that they don't have a
bomb.
Jon Karl.
The Press: Mr. President,
does it give you any pause
to see this deal praised by
Syrian dictator Assad as a
"great victory for Iran," or
praised by those in Tehran
who still shout "death
to America," and yet our
closest ally in the Middle
East calls it "a mistake of
historic proportions"?
And here in Congress, it
looks like a large majority
will vote to
reject this deal.
I know you can veto that
rejection, but do you have
any concerns about seeing
a majority of the people's
representatives in
Congress saying that this
is a bad deal?
And if I can just ask you
quick political question, a
very quick one.
The President: Jon, I think
-- The Press: Donald -- The
President: Let me answer the
question that you asked.
It does not give me pause
that Mr. Assad or others in
Tehran may be trying to spin
the deal in a way that they
think is favorable to what
their constituencies want to
hear.
That's what politicians do.
And that's been the
case throughout.
I mean, you'll recall that
during the course of these
negotiations over the last
couple of months every time
the Supreme Leader or
somebody tweeted something
out, for some reason we all
bought into the notion,
well, the Obama
administration must be
giving this or
capitulating to that.
Well, now we have a
document so you can see
what the deal is.
We don't have to speculate,
we don't have to engage in
spin, you can just read
what it says and what is
required.
And nobody has disputed that
as a consequence of this
agreement Iran has to
drastically reduce its
stockpiles of uranium, is
cut off from plutonium; the
Fordow facility that is
underground is converted;
that we have an
unprecedented inspections
regime; that we have
snap-back provisions
if they cheat.
The facts are the facts.
And I'm not concerned about
what others say about it.
Now, with respect to
Congress, my hope -- I won't
prejudge this -- my hope is,
is that everyone in Congress
also evaluates this
agreement based on the facts
-- not on politics, not on
posturing, not on the fact
that this is a deal I bring
to Congress as opposed to a
Republican President, not
based on lobbying, but based
on what's in the national
interest of the United
States of America.
And I think that if Congress
does that, then, in fact,
based on the facts, the
majority of Congress should
approve of this deal.
But we live in Washington
and politics do intrude.
And as I said in an
interview yesterday, I am
not betting on the
Republican Party rallying
behind this agreement.
I do expect the debate to
be based on facts and not
speculation or
misinformation.
And that I welcome -- in
part because, look, there
are legitimate
real concerns here.
We've already
talked about it.
We have huge
differences with Iran.
Israel has legitimate
concerns about its security
relative to Iran.
You have a large country
with a significant military
that has proclaimed that
Israel shouldn't exist, that
has denied the Holocaust,
that has financed Hezbollah,
and as a consequence there
are missiles that are
pointed towards Tel Aviv.
And so I think there are
very good reasons why
Israelis are nervous about
Iran's position in the world
generally.
And I've said this to Prime
Minister Netanyahu, I've
said it directly to
the Israeli people.
But what I've also said is
that all those threats are
compounded if Iran
gets a nuclear weapon.
And for all the objections
of Prime Minister Netanyahu,
or, for that matter, some of
the Republican leadership
that's already spoken, none
of them have presented to
me, or the American people,
a better alternative.
I'm hearing a lot of talking
points being repeated about
"this is a bad deal" --
"this is a historically bad
deal," "this will threaten
Israel and threaten the
world and threaten
the United States."
I mean, there's
been a lot of that.
What I haven't heard is,
what is your preferred
alternative?
If 99 percent of the world
community and the majority
of nuclear experts look at
this thing and they say,
this will prevent Iran from
getting a nuclear bomb, and
you are arguing either that
it does not, or that even if
it does it's temporary, or
that because they're going
to get a windfall of their
accounts being unfrozen that
they'll cause more problems,
then you should have some
alternative to present.
And I haven't heard that.
And the reason is because
there really are only two
alternatives here: Either
the issue of Iran obtaining
a nuclear weapon is resolved
diplomatically through a
negotiation, or it's
resolved through force,
through war.
Those are the options.
Now, you'll hear some
critics say, well, we could
have negotiated
a better deal.
Okay.
What does that mean?
I think the suggestion among
a lot of the critics has
been that a better deal, an
acceptable deal would be one
in which Iran has no nuclear
capacity at all, peaceful or
otherwise.
The problem with that
position is that there is
nobody who thinks that Iran
would or could ever accept
that, and the international
community does not take the
view that Iran can't have a
peaceful nuclear program.
They agree with us
that Iran cannot have
a nuclear weapon.
And so we don't have
diplomatic leverage to
eliminate every vestige
of a peaceful nuclear
program in Iran.
What we do have the leverage
to do is to make sure they
don't have a weapon.
That's exactly
what we've done.
So to go back to Congress,
I challenge those who are
objecting to this agreement,
number one, to read the
agreement before they
comment on it; number two,
to explain specifically
where it is that they think
this agreement does not
prevent Iran from getting a
nuclear weapon, and why
they're right and people
like Ernie Moniz, who is an
MIT nuclear physicist and an
expert in these issues, is
wrong, why the rest of the
world is wrong, and then
present an alternative.
And if the alternative is
that we should bring Iran to
heel through military force,
then those critics should
say so.
And that will be
an honest debate.
All right.
The Press: Mr.
President, if I can --
The President: No, no --
The Press: Prime
Minister Netanyahu said that
you have a situation where
Iran can delay 24 days
before giving access to
military facilities --
The President: I'm happy to
-- that's a good example.
So let's take the
issue of 24 days.
This has been I think
swirling today, the notion
that this is insufficient
in terms of inspections.
Now, keep in mind, first of
all, that we'll have 24/7
inspections of declared
nuclear facilities --
Fordow, Natanz, Arak, their
uranium mines; facilities
that are known to produce
centrifuges, parts.
That entire infrastructure
that we know about we will
have sophisticated, 24/7
monitoring of those
facilities.
So then the issue is, what
if they try to develop a
covert program?
Now, one of the advantages
of having inspections across
the entire production chain
is that it makes it very
difficult to set up
a covert program.
There are only so many
uranium mines in Iran.
And if, in fact, we're
counting the amount of
uranium that's being mined
and suddenly some is missing
on the back end, they got
some explaining to do.
So we're able to track
what's happening along the
existing facilities to make
sure that there is not
diversion into a
covert program.
But let's say that Iran is
so determined that it now
wants to operate covertly.
The IAEA, the international
organization charged with
implementing the
non-proliferation treaty and
monitoring nuclear
activities in countries
around the world -- the IAEA
will have the ability to
say, that undeclared site
we're concerned about, we
see something suspicious.
And they will be able to
say to Iran, we want to go
inspect that.
Now, if Iran objects,
we can override it.
In the agreement, we've set
it up so we can override
Iran's objection.
And we don't need Russia or
China in order for us to get
that override.
And if they continue to
object, we're in a position
to snap back sanctions and
declare that Iran is in
violation and is cheating.
As for the fact that it may
take 24 days to finally get
access to the site, the
nature of nuclear programs
and facilities is such, this
is not something you hide in
a closet.
This is not something you
put on a dolly and kind of
wheel off somewhere.
And, by the way, if we
identify an undeclared site
that we're suspicious about,
we're going to be keeping
eyes on it.
So we're going to be
monitoring what the activity
is, and that's going to
be something that will be
evidence if we think that
some funny business was
going on there that we
can then present to the
international community.
So we'll be monitoring
that that entire time.
And, by the way, if there
is nuclear material on that
site, high school physics
will remind us that that
leaves a trace.
And so we'll know that, in
fact, there was a violation
of the agreement.
So the point is, Jonathan,
that this is the most
vigorous inspection and
verification regime by far
that has ever
been negotiated.
Is it possible that Iran
decides to try to cheat
despite having this entire
inspection verification
mechanism?
It's possible.
But if it does, first of
all, we've built in a
one-year breakout time,
which gives us a year to
respond forcefully.
And we've built in a
snap-back provision so we
don't have to go through
lengthy negotiations at the
U.N.
to put the sanctions
right back in place.
And so really the only
argument you can make
against the verification and
inspection mechanism that
we've put forward is that
Iran is so intent on
obtaining a nuclear weapon
that no inspection regime
and no verification
mechanism would be
sufficient because they'd
find some way to get around
it because they're
untrustworthy.
And if that's your view,
then we go back to the
choice that you have
to make earlier.
That means, presumably,
that you can't negotiate.
And what you're really
saying is, is that you've
got to apply military force
to guarantee that they don't
have a nuclear program.
And if somebody wants to
make that debate -- whether
it's the Republican
leadership, or Prime
Minister Netanyahu, or
the Israeli Ambassador or
others, they're
free to make it.
But it's not persuasive.
Carol Lee.
The Press: Thank
you, Mr. President.
I want to ask you about the
arms and ballistic missile
embargo.
Why did you decide -- agree
to lift those even with the
five- and eight-year
durations?
It's obviously emerging as a
sticking point on the Hill.
And are you concerned that
arms to Iran will go to
Hezbollah or Hamas?
And is there anything that
you or a future President
can do to stop that?
And if you don't mind, I
wanted to see if you could
step back a little bit, and
when you look at this Iran
deal and all the other
issues and unrest that's
happening in the Middle
East, what kind of Middle
East do you want to leave
when you leave the White
House in a year and a half?
The President: So the issue
of the arms embargo and
ballistic missiles is of
real concern to us -- has
been of real concern to us.
And it is in the national
security interest of the
United States to prevent
Iran from sending weapons to
Hezbollah, for example,
or sending weapons to the
Houthis in Yemen that
accelerate a civil war
there.
We have a number of
mechanisms under
international law that give
us authority to interdict
arms shipments by Iran.
One of those
mechanisms is the U.N.
security resolution related
to Iran's nuclear program.
Essentially, Iran was
sanctioned because of what
had happened at Fordow, its
unwillingness to comply with
previous U.N.
security resolutions about
their nuclear program.
And as part of the package
of sanctions that was
slapped on them, the issue
of arms and ballistic
missiles were included.
Now, under the terms
of the original U.N.
resolution, the fact is
that once an agreement was
arrived at that gave the
international community
assurance Iran didn't have
a nuclear weapon, you could
argue just looking at the
text that those arms and
ballistic missile
prohibitions should
immediately go away.
But what I said to our
negotiators was given that
Iran has breached trust,
and the uncertainty of our
allies in the region about
Iran's activities, let's
press for a longer extension
of the arms embargo and the
ballistic missile
prohibitions.
And we got that.
We got five years in which,
under this new agreement,
arms coming in and out
of Iran are prohibited.
And we got eight years
with respect to ballistic
missiles.
But part of the reason why
we were willing to extend it
only for five, let's say, as
opposed to a longer period
of time, is because
we have other U.N.
resolutions that prohibit
arms sales by Iran to
organizations
like Hezbollah.
We have other U.N.
resolutions and multilateral
agreements that give us
authority to interdict
arms shipments from Iran
throughout the region.
And so we've had belts and
suspenders and buttons, a
whole bunch of different
legal authorities.
These legal authorities
under the nuclear program
may lapse after five or
eight years, but we'll still
be in possession of other
legal authorities that allow
us to interdict those arms.
And truthfully, these
prohibitions are not
self-enforcing.
It's not like the U.N.
has the capacity to police
what Iran is doing.
What it does is it
gives us authority under
international law to
prevent arms shipments from
happening in concert with
our allies and our partners.
And the real problem, if you
look at how, for example,
Hezbollah got a lot of
missiles that are a grave
threat to Israel and many of
our friends in the region,
it's not because
they were legal.
It's not because somehow
that was authorized under
international law.
It was because there was
insufficient intelligence,
or capacity, to stop
those shipments.
So the bottom line is,
Carol, I share the concerns
of Israel, Saudis, Gulf
partners about Iran shipping
arms and causing conflict
and chaos in the region.
And that's why I've said to
them, let's double down and
partner much more
effectively to improve our
intelligence capacity and
our interdiction capacity so
that fewer of those arms
shipments are getting
through the net.
But the legal authorities,
we'll still possess.
And obviously, we've got our
own unilateral prohibitions
and sanctions in place
around non-nuclear issues,
like support for Hezbollah.
And those remain in place.
Now, in terms of the larger
issues of the Middle East,
obviously that's a
longer discussion.
I think my key goal when I
turn over the keys to the
President -- the next
President -- is that we are
on track to defeat ISIL;
that they are much more
contained and we're moving
in the right direction
there.
That we have jumpstarted a
process to resolve the civil
war in Syria, which is like
an open sore in the region
and is giving refuge to
terrorist organizations who
are taking advantage
of that chaos.
To make sure that in Iraq
not only have we pushed back
ISIL, but we've also created
an environment in which
Sunni, Shia and Kurd are
starting to operate and
function more
effectively together.
And to be in a conversation
with all our partners in the
region about how we have
strengthened our security
partnerships so that they
feel they can address any
potential threats that may
come, including threats from
Iran.
And that includes providing
additional security
assurances and cooperation
to Israel, building on the
unprecedented cooperation
that we have already put in
place and support that
we've already put in place.
It includes the work that
we've done with the GCC up
at Camp David, making sure
that we execute that.
If we've done those things,
then the problems in the
Middle East will
not be solved.
And ultimately, it's not the
job of the President of the
United States to solve every
problem in the Middle East.
The people of the Middle
East are going to have to
solve some of these
problems themselves.
But I think we can provide
that next President at least
a foundation for continued
progress in these various
areas.
The last thing I would say
-- and this is a longer-term
issue -- is we have to
address the youth in the
region with jobs and
opportunity and a better
vision for the future so
that they are not tempted by
the nihilistic, violent
dead-end that organizations
like ISIL offer.
Again, we can't do that
entirely by ourselves, but
we can partner with
well-intentioned
organizations, states, NGOs,
religious leaders in the
region.
We have to do a better job
of that than we've been
doing so far.
Michael Crowley.
The Press: Thank you.
You alluded earlier to
Iran's role in Syria, just
to focus on that
for a moment.
Many analysts and some
former members of your
administration believe that
the kind of negotiated
political settlement that
you say is necessary in
Syria will require working
directly with Iran and
giving Iran an
important role.
Do you agree?
And is that a dialogue
you'll be actively seeking?
And what about the
fight against ISIS?
What would it take for there
to be explicit cooperation
between the U.S.
and Iran?
The President: I do agree
that we're not going to
solve the problems in Syria
unless there's buy-in from
the Russians, the Iranians,
the Turks, our Gulf
partners.
It's too chaotic.
There are too many factions.
There's too much money and
too many arms flooding into
the zone.
It's gotten caught up in
both sectarian conflict and
geopolitical jockeying.
And in order for us to
resolve it, there's going to
have to be agreement among
the major powers that are
interested in Syria that
this is not going to be won
on the battlefield.
So Iran is one of those
players, and I think that
it's important for
them to be part of that
conversation.
I want to repeat
what I said earlier.
We have not -- and I don't
anticipate any time in the
near future -- restored
normal diplomatic relations
with Iran.
And so I do not foresee a
formal set of agreements
with Iran in terms of
how we're conducting our
counter-ISIL campaign.
But clearly, Iran has
influence in Iraq.
Iraq has a majority
Shia population.
They have
relationships to Iran.
Some are natural.
We expect somebody like
Prime Minister Abadi to meet
with and negotiate and work
with Iran as its neighbor.
Some are less legitimate,
where you see Iran financing
Shia militias that in the
past have killed American
soldiers and in the future
may carry out atrocities
when they move
into Sunni areas.
And so we're working with
our diplomats on the ground,
as well as our military
teams on the ground to asses
where can we appropriately
at least de-conflict, and
where can we work with Prime
Minister Abadi around an
overall strategy for Iraq to
regain its sovereignty, and
where do we tell Abadi, you
know what, what Iran is
doing there is a problem,
and we can't cooperate in
that area, for example,
unless you get those folks
out of there because we're
not going to have our
troops, even in an advisory
or training role, looking
over their shoulders because
they're not sure of what
might happen to them.
And those conversations
have been ongoing.
I think they will continue.
The one thing you can count
on is that any work that the
U.S.
government does, or the U.S.
military does in Iraq with
other partners on the ground
is premised on the idea that
they are reporting to --
under the chain of command
of the Iraqi government and
Iraqi security forces.
If we don't have confidence
that ultimately Abadi is
directing those soldiers,
then it's tough for us to
have any kind of
direct relationship.
Major Garrett.
The Press: Thank
you, Mr. President.
As you well know, there are
four Americans in Iran --
three held on trumped-up
charges, according to your
administration; one,
whereabouts unknown.
Can you tell the country,
sir, why you are content,
with all the fanfare around
this deal, to leave the
conscience of this nation
and the strength of this
nation unaccounted for in
relation to these four
Americans?
And last week, the Chairman
of the Joint Chiefs of Staff
said, under no circumstances
should there be any relief
for Iran in terms of
ballistic missiles or
conventional weapons.
It is perceived that
that was a last-minute
capitulation in
these negotiations.
Many in the Pentagon feel
you've left the Chairman of
the Joint Chiefs of
Staff hung out to dry.
Could you comment?
The President: I got to give
you credit, Major, for how
you craft those questions.
The notion that I am content
as I celebrate with American
citizens languishing in
Iranian jails -- Major,
that's nonsense, and
you should know better.
I've met with the families
of some of those folks.
Nobody is content.
And our diplomats and our
teams are working diligently
to try to get them out.
Now, if the question is
why we did not tie the
negotiations to their
release, think about the
logic that that creates.
Suddenly, Iran realizes, you
know what, maybe we can get
additional concessions out
of the Americans by holding
these individuals.
It makes it much more
difficult for us to walk
away if Iran somehow thinks
that a nuclear deal is
dependent in some fashion
on the nuclear deal.
And, by the way, if we had
walked away from the nuclear
deal, we'd still be pushing
them just as hard to get
these folks out.
That's why those issues
are not connected.
But we are working every
single day to try to get
them out, and won't stop
until they're out and
rejoined with
their families.
With respect to the
Chairman's testimony, to
some degree I already
answered this with Carol.
We are not taking the
pressure off Iran with
respect to arms and with
respect to ballistic
missiles.
As I just explained, not
only do we keep in place for
five years the arms embargo
under this particular new
U.N.
resolution, not only do we
maintain the eight years on
the ballistic missiles
under this particular U.N.
resolution, but we have a
host of other multilateral
and unilateral authorities
that allow us to take action
where we see Iran engaged
in those activities whether
it's six years from now
or 10 years from now.
So we have not lost
those legal authorities.
And in fact, part of my
pitch to the GCC countries,
as well as to Prime Minister
Netanyahu, is we should do a
better job making sure that
Iran is not engaged in
sending arms to
organizations like
Hezbollah.
And as I just indicated,
that means improving our
intelligence capacity and
our interdiction capacity
with our partners.
April Ryan.
The Press: Thank
you, Mr. President.
I want to change
the subject a bit.
Earlier this year, on the
flight to Selma, you said,
on matters of race, as
President your job is to
close the remaining gaps
that are left in state and
federal government.
Now, how does criminal
justice reform fit into that
equation?
And what gaps remain for
you towards the end of
your presidency?
And also, what does it mean
to travel to Kenya, your
father's homeland, in the
next couple of weeks as
President to the
United States?
And lastly, would you revoke
the Medal of Freedom from
Bill Cosby?
The President: You stuffed
a lot in there, April.
(laughter)
The Press: I learned
from my colleagues.
The President: Say,
who did you learn from?
Jonathan Karl?
Is that what you said?
(laughter)
The Press: On criminal
justice reform, obviously I
gave a lengthy speech
yesterday, but this is
something that I've been
thinking about a lot; been
working first with Eric
Holder, now with Loretta
Lynch about -- we've been
working on along with other
prosecutors of the U.S.
Attorney's Office.
It's an outgrowth of the
task force that we put
together, post-Ferguson and
the Garner case in New York.
And I don't think that the
criminal justice system is
obviously the sole source
of racial tension in this
country, or the key
institution to resolving the
opportunity gap.
But I think it is a part
of the broader set of
challenges that we face in
creating a more perfect
union.
And the good news is, is
that this is one of those
rare issues where we've
got some Republican and
Democratic interest, as well
as federal, state, and local
interest in solving
the problem.
I think people recognize
that there are violent
criminals out there and
they've got to be locked up.
We've got to have tough
prosecutors, we have to
support our law
enforcement officials.
Police are in a tough job
and they are helping to keep
us safe, and we are grateful
and thankful to them.
But what we also know
is this huge spike in
incarcerations is also
driven by non-violent drug
offenses where the
sentencing is completely out
of proportion
with the crime.
And that costs taxpayers
enormous amounts of money.
It is debilitating
communities who are seeing
huge proportions of
the young men in their
communities finding
themselves with a criminal
record, rendering them
oftentimes unemployable.
So it compounds problems
that these communities
already have.
And so I am very
appreciative of folks like
Dick Durbin and Cory Booker,
alongside Mike Lee and Rand
Paul and other folks in
the House who are working
together to see if we can
both reduce some of these
mandatory minimums around
non-violent drug offenses.
Because again, I tend not to
have a lot of sympathy when
it comes to violent crime.
But when it comes to
non-violent drug offenses,
is there work that we can
do to reduce mandatory
minimums, create more
diversion programs like drug
courts?
Then, can we do a better job
on the rehabilitation side
inside of prisons so that we
are preparing these folks
who are eventually going to
be released to reenter the
workforce?
On the back end, are we
doing more to link them up
with reentry programs
that are effective?
And this may be an area
where we could have some
really significant
bipartisan legislation that
doesn't eliminate all the
other challenges we've got.
Because the most important
goal is keeping folks from
getting in the criminal
justice system in the first
place, which means early
childhood education and good
jobs, and making sure that
we're not segregating folks
in impoverished communities
that have no contact with
opportunity.
But this can make
a difference.
I met these four
ex-offenders, as I said,
yesterday, and what was
remarkable was how they had
turned their lives around.
And these were some folks
who had been some pretty
tough criminals.
One of them had served 10
years; another was a repeat
offender that had
served a lot of time.
And in each instance,
somebody intervened at some
point in their lives -- once
they had already been in the
criminal justice system,
once they had already gotten
in trouble -- and said, you
know what, I think you can
live a different way, and
I'm willing to help you.
And that one person, an art
teacher, or a GED teacher,
or somebody who was willing
to offer a guy a job -- I
want to give a shout-out to
Five Guys, because one of
the guys there was an
ex-felon, and Five Guys gave
him a job.
And he ended up becoming a
manager at the store and was
able to completely
turn his life around.
But the point was, somebody
reached out to that person
and gave him a chance.
And so part of our question
should be, how about
somebody reaching out to
these guys when they're 10,
or 11, or 12, or eight, as
opposed to waiting until
they've already gone through
a criminal justice program.
That's part of why we're
doing My Brother's Keeper.
But this is an area where I
feel modestly optimistic.
I think in the meantime
we've got to stay on top of
keeping the crime rate down,
because part of the reason I
think there's a conversation
taking place is violent
crime has
significantly dropped.
Last year, we saw both
incarcerations and the crime
rate drop, and this can
always turn if we start
seeing renewed problems in
terms of violent crime.
And there's parts of the
country where violent crime
is still a real problem,
including my hometown of
Chicago, and in Baltimore.
And part of what I've asked
Attorney General Lynch to do
is to figure out how can
we refocus attention.
If we're going to do a
package of criminal justice
reforms, part of it would be
actually having a greater
police presence and more
law enforcement in the
communities that are really
getting hit hard and haven't
seen some of the drops in
violent crime that we've
seen in places like
Manhattan, for example.
With respect to the visit
to Kenya, it's obviously
something I'm
looking forward to.
I'll be honest with you,
visiting Kenya as a private
citizen is probably more
meaningful to me than
visiting as President
because I can actually get
outside of a hotel room
or a conference center.
And just the logistics of
visiting a place are always
tough as President, but
it's obviously symbolically
important.
And my hope is, is that we
can deliver a message that
the U.S.
is a strong partner not
just for Kenya, but for
Sub-Saharan Africa
generally; build on the
progress that's been made
around issues of health and
education; focus on
counterterrorism issues that
are important in East Africa
because of al-Shabaab and
some of the tragedies that
have happened inside of
Kenya; and continue to
encourage democracy and the
reduction of corruption
inside that country that
sometimes has held back
this incredibly gifted and
blessed country.
And with respect to the
Medal of Freedom, there's no
precedent for
revoking a medal.
We don't have
that mechanism.
And as you know, I tend to
make it a policy not to
comment on the specifics
of cases where there might
still be, if not criminal,
then civil issues involved.
I'll say this: If you give a
woman -- or a man, for that
matter -- without his or her
knowledge, a drug, and then
have sex with that person
without consent, that's
rape.
And I think this country --
any civilized country --
should have no
tolerance for rape.
All right.
Have we exhausted
Iran questions here?
I think there's a
helicopter that's coming.
But I really am enjoying
this Iran debate.
Topics that may not
have been touched upon,
criticisms that you've heard
that I did not answer?
Go ahead.
I know Josh is getting a
little stressed here --
(laughter)
-- but I just want to make
sure that we're not leaving
any stones unturned here.
Go ahead.
The Press: Thanks,
Mr. President.
I'll be brief.
The argument has been made
that Iran now has a cash
windfall, billions to spend.
Your people seem confident
they're going to spend it at
home.
Why are you confident
they're not going to spend
it on arming Hezbollah,
arming Bashar al-Assad, et
cetera?
The President: I think
that's a great question and
I'm glad you brought it up.
I think it is a mistake to
characterize our belief that
they will just spend it on
daycare centers, and roads,
and paying down debt.
We think that they have to
do some of that, because
Rouhani was elected
specifically on the premise
of improving the economic
situation inside of Iran.
That economy has tanked
since we imposed sanctions.
So the notion that they're
just immediately going to
turn over $100 billion to
the IRGC or the Quds Force I
think runs contrary to all
the intelligence that we've
seen and the commitments
that the Iranian government
has made.
Do we think that with the
sanctions coming down, that
Iran will have some
additional resources for its
military and for some of the
activities in the region
that are a threat to us and
a threat to our allies?
I think that is a likelihood
that they've got some
additional resources.
Do I think it's a
game-changer for them?
No.
They are currently
supporting Hezbollah, and
there is a ceiling -- a pace
at which they could support
Hezbollah even more,
particularly in the chaos
that's taking
place in Syria.
So can they potentially
try to get more assistance
there?
Yes.
Should we put more resources
into blocking them from
getting that assistance
to Hezbollah?
Yes.
Is the incremental
additional money that
they've got to try to
destabilize the region or
send to their proxies, is
that more important than
preventing Iran from
getting a nuclear weapon?
No.
So I think -- again, this
is a matter of us making a
determination of
what is our priority.
The other problem with the
argument that folks have
been making about, oh, this
is a windfall and suddenly
Iran is flushed with cash,
and they're going to take
over the world.
And I say that not
tongue-in-cheek, because if
you look at some of the
statements by some of our
critics, you would think
that Iran is, in fact, going
to take over the world as a
consequence of this deal --
which I think would be
news to the Iranians.
That argument is also
premised on the notion that
if there is no deal, if
Congress votes down this
deal, that we're able to
keep sanctions in place with
the same vigor and
effectiveness as we have
right now.
And that, I can promise
you, is not true.
That is absolutely not true.
I want to repeat: We're
not writing Iran a check.
This is Iran's money that we
were able to block from them
having access to.
That required the
cooperation of countries all
around the world, many of
whom really want to purchase
oil from Iran.
The imposition of sanctions
-- their cooperation with us
-- has cost them billions of
dollars, made it harder for
them.
They've been willing to
do that because they've
believed we were sincere
about trying to resolve the
nuclear issue peacefully,
and they considered that a
priority -- a high enough
priority that they were
willing to cooperate
with us on sanctions.
If they saw us walking away,
or more specifically, if
they saw the U.S.
Congress effectively vetoing
the judgment of 99 percent
of the world community that
this is a deal that resolves
the Iranian weapons program
-- nuclear weapons program
in an equitable way, the
sanctions system unravels.
And so we could still
maintain some of our
unilateral sanctions, but it
would be far less effective
-- as it was before we were
able to put together these
multilateral sanctions.
So maybe they don't get $100
billion; maybe they get $60
billion or $70
billion instead.
The price for that that
we've paid is that now Iran
is pursuing a
nuclear weapon.
We have no inspectors
on the ground.
We don't know
what's going on.
They're still getting
some cash windfall.
We've lost credibility in
the eyes of the world.
We will have effectively
united Iran and divided
ourselves from our allies.
A terrible
position to be in.
I'm just going to look -- I
made some notes about any of
the arguments -- the other
arguments that I've
heard here.
The Press: What
about -- (off-mic)
-- the end of the deal?
The President: Okay,
yes, that's a good one.
The notion --
The Press: A
the end of the deal they
could go back --
The President:
Right.
Well, so let's address this
issue of -- because that's
the other big argument
that's been made.
All right, let's assume that
the deal holds for 10 years,
Iran doesn't cheat.
Now, at the end of 10 years,
some of the restrictions
have been lifted --
although, remember, others
stay in place for 15 years.
So for example, they've
still got to keep their
stockpiles at a minimal
level for 15 years.
The inspections don't go
away; those are still in
place 15, 20 years from now.
Their commitment under the
Non-Proliferation Treaty
does not go away;
that's still in place.
The additional protocol that
they have to sign up for
under this deal, which
requires a more extensive
inspection and verification
mechanism -- that stays in
place.
So there's no scenario
in which a U.S.
President is not in a
stronger position 12, 13, 15
years from now if, in fact,
Iran decided at that point
they still wanted to
get a nuclear weapon.
Keep in mind, we will have
maintained a one-year
breakout time, we will have
rolled back their program,
frozen their facilities,
kept them under severe
restrictions, had observers.
They will have made
international commitments
supported by countries
around the world.
And -- hold on a second --
and if at that point they
finally decided, you know
what, we're going to cheat,
or not even cheat -- at that
point, they decide openly
we're now pursuing a nuclear
weapon -- they're still in
violation of this deal and
the commitments they've made
internationally.
And so we are still in a
position to mobilize the
world community to say, no,
you can't have a nuclear
weapon.
And they're not in a
stronger position to get a
nuclear weapon at that
point; they're in a weaker
position than
they are today.
And, by the way, we haven't
given away any of our
military capabilities.
We're not in a weaker
position to respond.
So even if everything the
critics were saying was true
-- that at the end of 10
years, or 12 years, or 15
years, Iran now is in a
position to decide it wants
a nuclear weapon, that
they're at a breakout point
-- they won't be at a
breakout point that is more
dangerous than the breakout
point they're in right now.
They won't be at a breakout
point that is shorter than
the one that exists today.
And so why wouldn't we at
least make sure that for the
next 10, 15, years they are
not getting a nuclear weapon
and we can verify it; and
afterwards, if they decide
if they've changed their
mind, we are then much more
knowledgeable about what
their capabilities are, much
more knowledgeable about
what their program is, and
still in a position to take
whatever actions we would
take today?
The Press: So none of this
is holding out hope that
they'll change
their behavior?
The President: No.
The Press: Nothing different
-- The President: No.
Look, I'm always hopeful
that behavior may change for
the sake of the Iranian
people as well as people in
the region.
There are young people there
who are not getting the
opportunities they deserve
because of conflict, because
of sectarianism, because of
poor governance, because of
repression, because
of terrorism.
And I remain eternally
hopeful that we can do
something about that, and
it should be part of U.S.
foreign policy to do
something about that.
But I'm not banking on that
to say that this deal is the
right thing to do.
Again, it is incumbent on
the critics of this deal to
explain how an American
President is in a worse
position 12, 13, 14, 15
years from now if, in fact,
at that point Iran says
we're going to pull out of
the NPT, kick out inspectors
and go for a nuclear bomb.
If that happens, that
President will be in a
better position than what
happened if Iran, as a
consequence of Congress
rejecting this deal, decides
that's it, we're done
negotiating, we're going
after a bomb right now.
The choices would be tougher
today than they would be for
that President 15
years from now.
And I have not yet heard
logic that refutes that.
All right.
I really have to go now.
I think we've hit
the big themes.
But I promise you, I
will address this again.
All right?
I suspect this is not the
last that we've heard of
this debate.