Thank you. Thank you So Much. Thank you. Thank
you so much. Madam Chairwoman, thank you so
much for your kind words and your leadership.
To Prime Minister Hailemariam, and the people
of Ethiopia -- once again, thank you for your
wonderful hospitality and for hosting this
pan-African institution. (Applause.) To members
of the African Union, distinguished guests,
ladies and gentlemen -- thank you for welcoming
me here today. It is a great honor to be the
first President of the United States to address
the African Union. (Applause.)
I’m grateful for this opportunity to speak
to the representatives of more than one billion
people of the great African continent. (Applause.)
We’re joined today by citizens, by leaders
of civil society, by faith communities, and
I’m especially pleased to see so many young
people who embody the energy and optimism
of today’s Africa. Hello! Thank you for
being here. (Applause.)
I stand before you as a proud American. I
also stand before you as the son of an African.
(Applause.) Africa and its people helped to
shape America and allowed it to become the
great nation that it is. And Africa and its
people have helped shape who I am and how
I see the world. In the villages in Kenya
where my father was born, I learned of my
ancestors, and the life of my grandfather,
the dreams of my father, the bonds of family
that connect us all as Africans and Americans.
As parents, Michelle and I want to make sure
that our two daughters know their heritage
-- European and African, in all of its strengths
and all of its struggle. So we’ve taken
our daughters and stood with them on the shores
of West Africa, in those doors of no return,
mindful that their ancestors were both slaves
and slave owners. We’ve stood with them
in that small cell on Robben Island where
Madiba showed the world that, no matter the
nature of his physical confinement, he alone
was the master of his fate. (Applause.) For
us, for our children, Africa and its people
teach us a powerful lesson -- that we must
uphold the inherent dignity of every human
being.
Dignity -- that basic idea that by virtue
of our common humanity, no matter where we
come from, or what we look like, we are all
born equal, touched by the grace of God. (Applause.)
Every person has worth. Every person matters.
Every person deserves to be treated with decency
and respect. Throughout much of history, mankind
did not see this. Dignity was seen as a virtue
reserved to those of rank and privilege, kings
and elders. It took a revolution of the spirit,
over many centuries, to open our eyes to the
dignity of every person. And around the world,
generations have struggled to put this idea
into practice in laws and in institutions.
So, too, here in Africa. This is the cradle
of humanity, and ancient African kingdoms
were home to great libraries and universities.
But the evil of slavery took root not only
abroad, but here on the continent. Colonialism
skewed Africa’s economy and robbed people
of their capacity to shape their own destiny.
Eventually, liberation movements grew. And
50 years ago, in a great burst of self-determination,
Africans rejoiced as foreign flags came down
and your national flags went up. (Applause.)
As South Africa’s Albert Luthuli said at
the time, “the basis for peace and brotherhood
in Africa is being restored by the resurrection
of national sovereignty and independence,
of equality and the dignity of man.”
A half-century into this independence era,
it is long past time to put aside old stereotypes
of an Africa forever mired in poverty and
conflict. The world must recognize Africa’s
extraordinary progress. Today, Africa is one
of the fastest-growing regions in the world.
Africa’s middle class is projected to grow
to more than one billion consumers. (Applause.)
With hundreds of millions of mobile phones,
surging access to the Internet, Africans are
beginning to leapfrog old technologies into
new prosperity. Africa is on the move, a new
Africa is emerging.
Propelled by this progress, and in partnership
with the world, Africa has achieved historic
gains in health. The rate of new HIV/AIDS
infections has plummeted. African mothers
are more likely to survive childbirth and
have healthy babies. Deaths from malaria have
been slashed, saving the lives of millions
of African children. Millions have been lifted
from extreme poverty. Africa has led the world
in sending more children to school. In other
words, more and more African men, women and
children are living with dignity and with
hope. (Applause.)
And Africa’s progress can also be seen in
the institutions that bring us together today.
When I first came to Sub-Saharan Africa as
a President, I said that Africa doesn’t
need strongmen, it needs strong institutions.
(Applause.) And one of those institutions
can be the African Union. Here, you can come
together, with a shared commitment to human
dignity and development. Here, your 54 nations
pursue a common vision of an “integrated,
prosperous and peaceful Africa.”
As Africa changes, I’ve called on the world
to change its approach to Africa. (Applause.)
So many Africans have told me, we don’t
want just aid, we want trade that fuels progress.
We don’t want patrons, we want partners
who help us build our own capacity to grow.
(Applause.) We don’t want the indignity
of dependence, we want to make our own choices
and determine our own future.
As President, I’ve worked to transform America’s
relationship with Africa -- so that we’re
truly listening to our African friends and
working together, as equal partners. And I’m
proud of the progress that we’ve made. We’ve
boosted American exports to this region, part
of trade that supports jobs for Africans and
Americans. To sustain our momentum -- and
with the bipartisan support of some of the
outstanding members of Congress who are here
today -- 20 of them who are here today -- I
recently signed the 10-year renewal of the
African Growth and Opportunity Act. (Applause.)
And I want to thank them all. Why don't they
stand very briefly so you can see them, because
they’ve done outstanding work. (Applause.)
We’ve launched major initiatives to promote
food security, and public health and access
to electricity, and to prepare the next generation
of African leaders and entrepreneurs --investments
that will help fuel Africa’s rise for decades
to come. Last year, as the Chairwoman noted,
I welcomed nearly 50 African presidents and
prime ministers to Washington so we could
begin a new chapter of cooperation. And by
coming to the African Union today, I’m looking
to build on that commitment.
I believe Africa’s rise is not just important
for Africa, it's important to the entire world.
We will not be able to meet the challenges
of our time -- from ensuring a strong global
economy to facing down violent extremism,
to combating climate change, to ending hunger
and extreme poverty -- without the voices
and contributions of one billion Africans.
(Applause.)
Now, even with Africa’s impressive progress,
we must acknowledge that many of these gains
rest on a fragile foundation. Alongside new
wealth, hundreds of millions of Africans still
endure extreme poverty. Alongside high-tech
hubs of innovation, many Africans are crowded
into shantytowns without power or running
water -- a level of poverty that’s an assault
on human dignity.
Moreover, as the youngest and fastest-growing
continent, Africa’s population in the coming
decades will double to some two billion people,
and many of them will be young, under 18.
Now, on the one hand, this could bring tremendous
opportunities as these young Africans harness
new technologies and ignite new growth and
reforms. Economists will tell you that countries,
regions, continents grow faster with younger
populations. It's a demographic edge and advantage
-- but only if those young people are being
trained. We need only to look at the Middle
East and North Africa to see that large numbers
of young people with no jobs and stifled voices
can fuel instability and disorder.
I suggest to you that the most urgent task
facing Africa today and for decades ahead
is to create opportunity for this next generation.
(Applause.) And this will be an enormous undertaking.
Africa will need to generate millions more
jobs than it’s doing right now. And time
is of the essence. The choices made today
will shape the trajectory of Africa, and therefore,
the world for decades to come. And as your
partner and your friend, allow me to suggest
several ways that we can meet this challenge
together.
Africa’s progress will depend on unleashing
economic growth -- not just for the few at
the top, but for the many, because an essential
element of dignity is being able to live a
decent life. (Applause.) That begins with
a job. And that requires trade and investment.
Many of your nations have made important reforms
to attract investment -- it’s been a spark
for growth. But in many places across Africa,
it’s still too hard to start a venture,
still too hard to build a business. Governments
that take additional reforms to make doing
business easier will have an eager partner
in the United States. (Applause.)
And that includes reforms to help Africa trade
more with itself -- as the Chairwoman and
I discussed before we came out here today
-- because the biggest markets for your goods
are often right next door. You don't have
to just look overseas for growth, you can
look internally. And our work to help Africa
modernize customs and border crossings started
with the East African Community -- now we’re
expanding our efforts across the continent,
because it shouldn’t be harder for African
countries to trade with each other than it
is for you to trade with Europe and America.
(Applause.)
Now, most U.S. trade with the region is with
just three countries -- South Africa, Nigeria
and Angola -- and much of that is in the form
of energy. I want Africans and Americans doing
more business together in more sectors, in
more countries. So we’re increasing trade
missions to places like Tanzania, Ethiopia
Mozambique. We’re working to help more Africans
get their goods to market. Next year, we’ll
host another U.S.-Africa Business Forum to
mobilize billions of dollars in new trade
and investment -- so we’re buying more of
each other’s products and all growing together.
Now, the United States isn’t the only country
that sees your growth as an opportunity. And
that is a good thing. When more countries
invest responsibly in Africa, it creates more
jobs and prosperity for us all. So I want
to encourage everybody to do business with
Africa, and African countries should want
to do business with every country. But economic
relationships can’t simply be about building
countries’ infrastructure with foreign labor
or extracting Africa’s natural resources.
Real economic partnerships have to be a good
deal for Africa -- they have to create jobs
and capacity for Africans. (Applause.)
And that includes the point that Chairwoman
Zuma made about illicit flows with multinationals
-- which is one of the reasons that we've
been a leading advocate, working with the
G7, to assist in making sure that there’s
honest accounting when businesses are investing
here in Africa, and making sure that capital
flows are properly accounted for. That's the
kind of partnership America offers.
Nothing will unlock Africa’s economic potential
more than ending the cancer of corruption.
(Applause.) And you are right that it is not
just a problem of Africa, it is a problem
of those who do business with Africa. It is
not unique to Africa -- corruption exists
all over the world, including in the United
States. But here in Africa, corruption drains
billions of dollars from economies that can't
afford to lose billions of dollars -- that's
money that could be used to create jobs and
build hospitals and schools. And when someone
has to pay a bribe just to start a business
or go to school, or get an official to do
the job they’re supposed to be doing anyway
-- that’s not “the African way.” (Applause.)
It undermines the dignity of the people you
represent.
Only Africans can end corruption in their
countries. As African governments commit to
taking action, the United States will work
with you to combat illicit financing, and
promote good governance and transparency and
rule of law. And we already have strong laws
in place that say to U.S. companies, you can't
engage in bribery to try to get business -- which
not all countries have. And we actually enforce
it and police it.
And let me add that criminal networks are
both fueling corruption and threatening Africa’s
precious wildlife -- and with it, the tourism
that many African economies count on. So America
also stands with you in the fight against
wildlife trafficking. That's something that
has to be addressed. (Applause.)
But, ultimately, the most powerful antidote
to the old ways of doing things is this new
generation of African youth. History shows
that the nations that do best are the ones
that invest in the education of their people.
(Applause.) You see, in this information age,
jobs can flow anywhere, and they typically
will flow to where workers are literate and
highly skilled and online. And Africa’s
young people are ready to compete. I've met
them -- they are hungry, they are eager. They’re
willing to work hard. So we've got to invest
in them. As Africa invests in education, our
entrepreneurship programs are helping innovators
start new businesses and create jobs right
here in Africa. And the men and women in our
Young African Leaders Initiative today will
be the leaders who can transform business
and civil society and governments tomorrow.
Africa’s progress will depend on development
that truly lifts countries from poverty to
prosperity -- because people everywhere deserve
the dignity of a life free from want. A child
born in Africa today is just as equal and
just as worthy as a child born in Asia or
Europe or America. At the recent development
conference here in Addis, African leadership
helped forge a new global compact for financing
that fuels development. And under the AU’s
leadership, the voice of a united Africa will
help shape the world’s next set of development
goals, and you’re pursuing a vision of the
future that you want for Africa.
And America’s approach to development -- the
central focus of our engagement with Africa
-- is focused on helping you build your own
capacity to realize that vision. Instead of
just shipping food aid to Africa, we’ve
helped more than two million farmers use new
techniques to boost their yields, feed more
people, reduce hunger. With our new alliance
of government and the private sector investing
billions of dollars in African agriculture,
I believe we can achieve our goal and lift
50 million Africans from poverty.
Instead of just sending aid to build power
plants, our Power Africa initiative is mobilizing
billions of dollars in investments from governments
and businesses to reduce the number of Africans
living without electricity. Now, an undertaking
of this magnitude will not be quick. It will
take many years. But working together, I believe
we can bring electricity to more than 60 million
African homes and businesses and connect more
Africans to the global economy. (Applause.)
Instead of just telling Africa, you’re on
your own, in dealing with climate change,
we’re delivering new tools and financing
to more than 40 African nations to help them
prepare and adapt. By harnessing the wind
and sun, your vast geothermal energy and rivers
for hydropower, you can turn this climate
threat into an economic opportunity. And I
urge Africa to join us in rejecting old divides
between North and South so we can forge a
strong global climate agreement this year
in Paris. Because sparing some of the world’s
poorest people from rising seas, more intense
droughts, shortages of water and food is a
matter of survival and a matter of human dignity.
Instead of just sending medicine, we’re
investing in better treatments and helping
Africa prevent and treat diseases. As the
United States continues to provide billions
of dollars in the fight against HIV/AIDS,
and as your countries take greater ownership
of health programs, we’re moving toward
a historic accomplishment -- the first AIDS-free
generation. (Applause.) And if the world learned
anything from Ebola, it’s that the best
way to prevent epidemics is to build strong
public health systems that stop diseases from
spreading in the first place. So America is
proud to partner with the AU and African countries
in this mission. Today, I can announce that
of the $1 billion that the United States is
devoting to this work globally, half will
support efforts here in Africa. (Applause.)
I believe Africa’s progress will also depend
on democracy, because Africans, like people
everywhere, deserve the dignity of being in
control of their own lives. (Applause.) We
all know what the ingredients of real democracy
are. They include free and fair elections,
but also freedom of speech and the press,
freedom of assembly. These rights are universal.
They’re written into African constitutions.
(Applause.) The African Charter on Human and
Peoples Rights declares that “every individual
shall have the right to the respect of the
dignity inherent in a human being.” From
Sierra Leone, Ghana, Benin, to Botswana, Namibia,
South Africa, democracy has taken root. In
Nigeria, more than 28 million voters bravely
cast their ballots and power transferred as
it should -- peacefully. (Applause.)
Yet at this very moment, these same freedoms
are denied to many Africans. And I have to
proclaim, democracy is not just formal elections.
(Applause.) When journalists are put behind
bars for doing their jobs, or activists are
threatened as governments crack down on civil
society -- (applause) -- then you may have
democracy in name, but not in substance. (Applause.)
And I'm convinced that nations cannot realize
the full promise of independence until they
fully protect the rights of their people.
And this is true even for countries that have
made important democratic progress. As I indicated
during my visit to Kenya, the remarkable gains
that country has made with a new constitution,
with its election, cannot be jeopardized by
restrictions on civil society. Likewise, our
host, Ethiopians have much to be proud of
-- I've been amazed at all the wonderful work
that's being done here -- and it's true that
the elections that took place here occurred
without violence. But as I discussed with
Prime Minister Hailemariam, that’s just
the start of democracy. I believe Ethiopia
will not fully unleash the potential of its
people if journalists are restricted or legitimate
opposition groups can't participate in the
campaign process. And, to his credit, the
Prime Minister acknowledged that more work
will need to be done for Ethiopia to be a
full-fledged, sustainable democracy. (Applause.)
So these are conversations we have to have
as friends. Our American democracy is not
perfect. We've worked for many years -- (applause)
-- but one thing we do is we continually reexamine
to figure out how can we make our democracy
better. And that's a force of strength for
us, being willing to look and see honestly
what we need to be doing to fulfill the promise
of our founding documents.
And every country has to go through that process.
No country is perfect, but we have to be honest,
and strive to expand freedoms, to broaden
democracy. The bottom line is that when citizens
cannot exercise their rights, the world has
a responsibility to speak out. And America
will, even if it’s sometimes uncomfortable
-- (applause) -- even when it’s sometimes
directed toward our friends.
And I know that there’s some countries that
don't say anything -- (laughter) -- and maybe
that's easier for leaders to deal with. (Laughter.)
But you're kind of stuck with us -- this is
how we are. (Applause.) We believe in these
things and we're going to keep on talking
about them.
And I want to repeat, we do this not because
we think our democracy is perfect, or we think
that every country has to follow precisely
our path. For more than two centuries since
our independence, we’re still working on
perfecting our union. We're not immune from
criticism. When we fall short of our ideals,
we strive to do better. (Applause.) But when
we speak out for our principles, at home and
abroad, we stay true to our values and we
help lift up the lives of people beyond our
borders. And we think that's important. And
it's especially important, I believe, for
those of us of African descent, because we've
known what it feels like to be on the receiving
end of injustice. We know what it means to
be discriminated against. (Applause.) We know
what it means to be jailed. So how can we
stand by when it's happening to somebody else?
I'll be frank with you, it can't just be America
that's talking about these things. Fellow
African countries have to talk about these
things. (Applause.) Just as other countries
championed your break from colonialism, our
nations must all raise our voices when universal
rights are being denied. For if we truly believe
that Africans are equal in dignity, then Africans
have an equal right to freedoms that are universal
-- that’s a principle we all have to defend.
(Applause.) And it's not just a Western idea;
it's a human idea.
I have to also say that Africa’s democratic
progress is also at risk when leaders refuse
to step aside when their terms end. (Applause.)
Now, let me be honest with you -- I do not
understand this. (Laughter.) I am in my second
term. It has been an extraordinary privilege
for me to serve as President of the United
States. I cannot imagine a greater honor or
a more interesting job. I love my work. But
under our Constitution, I cannot run again.
(Laughter and applause.) I can't run again.
I actually think I'm a pretty good President
-- I think if I ran I could win. (Laughter
and applause.) But I can't.
So there’s a lot that I'd like to do to
keep America moving, but the law is the law.
(Applause.) And no one person is above the
law. Not even the President. (Applause.) And
I'll be honest with you -- I’m looking forward
to life after being President. (Laughter.)
I won't have such a big security detail all
the time. (Laughter.) It means I can go take
a walk. I can spend time with my family. I
can find other ways to serve. I can visit
Africa more often. (Applause.) The point is,
I don't understand why people want to stay
so long. (Laughter.) Especially when they’ve
got a lot of money. (Laughter and applause.)
When a leader tries to change the rules in
the middle of the game just to stay in office,
it risks instability and strife -- as we’ve
seen in Burundi. (Applause.) And this is often
just a first step down a perilous path. And
sometimes you’ll hear leaders say, well,
I'm the only person who can hold this nation
together. (Laughter.) If that's true, then
that leader has failed to truly build their
nation. (Applause.)
You look at Nelson Mandela -- Madiba, like
George Washington, forged a lasting legacy
not only because of what they did in office,
but because they were willing to leave office
and transfer power peacefully. (Applause.)
And just as the African Union has condemned
coups and illegitimate transfers of power,
the AU’s authority and strong voice can
also help the people of Africa ensure that
their leaders abide by term limits and their
constitutions. (Applause.) Nobody should be
president for life.
And your country is better off if you have
new blood and new ideas. (Applause.) I'm still
a pretty young man, but I know that somebody
with new energy and new insights will be good
for my country. (Applause.) It will be good
for yours, too, in some cases.
Africa’s progress will also depend on security
and peace -- because an essential part of
human dignity is being safe and free from
fear. In Angola, Mozambique, Liberia, Sierra
Leone, we’ve seen conflicts end and countries
work to rebuild. But from Somalia and Nigeria
to Mali and Tunisia, terrorists continue to
target innocent civilians. Many of these groups
claim the banner of religion, but hundreds
of millions of African Muslims know that Islam
means peace. (Applause.) And we must call
groups
like al Qaeda, ISIL, al-Shabaab, Boko Haram
-- we must call them what they are -- murderers.
(Applause.)
In the face of threats, Africa -- and the
African Union --has shown leadership. Because
of the AU force in Somalia,
al-Shabaab controls less territory and the
Somali government is growing stronger. In
central Africa, the AU-led mission continues
to degrade the Lord’s Resistance Army. In
the Lake Chad Basin, forces from several nations
-- with the backing of the AU -- are fighting
to end Boko Haram’s senseless brutality.
And today, we salute all those who serve to
protect the innocent, including so many brave
African peacekeepers.
Now, as Africa stands against terror and conflict,
I want you to know that the United States
stands with you. With training and support,
we’re helping African forces grow stronger.
The United States is supporting the AU’s
efforts to strengthen peacekeeping, and we’re
working with countries in the region to deal
with emerging crises with the African Peacekeeping
Rapid Response Partnership.
The world must do more to help as well. This
fall at the United Nations, I will host a
summit to secure new commitments to strengthen
international support for peacekeeping, including
here in Africa. And building on commitments
that originated here in the AU, we’ll work
to develop a new partnership between the U.N.
and the AU that can provide reliable support
for AU peace operations. If African governments
and international partners step up with strong
support, we can transform how we work together
to promote security and peace in Africa.
Our efforts to ensure our shared security
must be matched by a commitment to improve
governance. Those things are connected. Good
governance is one of the best weapons against
terrorism and instability. Our fight against
terrorist groups, for example, will never
be won if we fail to address legitimate grievances
that terrorists may try to exploit, if we
don’t build trust with all communities,
if we don’t uphold the rule of law. There’s
a saying, and I believe it is true -- if we
sacrifice liberty in the name of security,
we risk losing both. (Applause.)
This same seriousness of purpose is needed
to end conflicts. In the Central African Republic,
the spirit of dialogue recently shown by ordinary
citizens must be matched by leaders committed
to inclusive elections and a peaceful transition.
In Mali, the comprehensive peace agreement
must be fulfilled. And leaders in Sudan must
know their nation will never truly thrive
so long as they wage war against their own
people -- the world will not forget about
Darfur.
In South Sudan, the joy of independence has
descended into the despair of violence. I
was there at the United Nations when we held
up South Sudan as the promise of a new beginning.
And neither Mr. Kiir, nor Mr. Machar have
shown, so far, any interest in sparing their
people from this suffering, or reaching a
political solution.
Yesterday, I met with leaders from this region.
We agree that, given the current situation,
Mr. Kiir and Mr. Machar must reach an agreement
by August 17th -- because if they do not,
I believe the international community must
raise the costs of intransigence. And the
world awaits the report of the AU Commission
of Inquiry, because accountability for atrocities
must be part of any lasting peace in Africa’s
youngest nation. (Applause.)
And finally, Africa’s progress will depend
on upholding the human rights of all people
-- for if each of us is to be treated with
dignity, each of us must be sure to also extend
that same dignity to others. As President,
I make it a point to meet with many of our
Young African Leaders. And one was a young
man from Senegal. He said something wonderful
about being together with so many of his African
brothers and sisters. He said, “Here, I
have met Africa, the [Africa] I’ve always
believed in. She’s beautiful. She’s young.
She’s full of talent and motivation and
ambition.” I agree.
Africa is the beautiful, talented daughters
who are just as capable as Africa’s sons.
(Applause.) And as a father, I believe that
my two daughters have to have the same chance
to pursue their dreams as anybody’s son
-- and that same thing holds true for girls
here in Africa. (Applause.) Our girls have
to be treated the same.
We can’t let old traditions stand in the
way. The march of history shows that we have
the capacity to broaden our moral imaginations.
We come to see that some traditions are good
for us, they keep us grounded, but that, in
our modern world, other traditions set us
back. When African girls are subjected to
the mutilation of their bodies, or forced
into marriage at the ages of 9 or 10 or 11
-- that sets us back. That's not a good tradition.
It needs to end. (Applause.)
When more than 80 percent of new HIV cases
in the hardest-hit countries are teenage girls,
that’s a tragedy; that sets us back. So
America is beginning a partnership with 10
African countries -- Kenya, Lesotho, Malawi,
Mozambique, South Africa, Swaziland, Tanzania,
Uganda, Zambia and Zimbabwe -- to keep teenage
girls safe and AIDS-free. (Applause.) And
when girls cannot go to school and grow up
not knowing how to read or write -- that denies
the world future women engineers, future women
doctors, future women business owners, future
women presidents -- that sets us all back.
(Applause.) That's a bad tradition -- not
providing our girls the same education as
our sons.
I was saying in Kenya, nobody would put out
a football team and then just play half the
team. You’d lose. (Applause.) the same is
true when it comes to getting everybody and
education. You can't leave half the team off
-- our young women. So as part of America’s
support for the education and the health of
our daughters, my wife, Michelle, is helping
to lead a global campaign, including a new
effort in Tanzania and Malawi, with a simple
message -- Let Girls Learn -- let girls learn
so they grow up healthy and they grow up strong.
(Applause.) And that will be good for families.
And they will raise smart, healthy children,
and that will be good for every one of your
nations.
Africa is the beautiful, strong women that
these girls grow up to become. The single
best indicator of whether a nation will succeed
is how it treats its women. (Applause.) When
women have health care and women have education,
families are stronger, communities are more
prosperous, children do better in school,
nations are more prosperous. Look at the amazing
African women here in this hall. (Applause.)
If you want your country to grow and succeed,
you have to empower your women. And if you
want to empower more women, America will be
your partner. (Applause.)
Let’s work together to stop sexual assault
and domestic violence. Let’s make clear
that we will not tolerate rape as a weapon
of war -- it’s a crime. (Applause.) And
those who commit it must be punished. Let’s
lift up the next generation of women leaders
who can help fight injustice and forge peace
and start new businesses and create jobs -- and
some might hire some men, too. (Laughter.)
We’ll all be better off when women have
equal futures.
And Africa is the beautiful tapestry of your
cultures and ethnicities and races and religions.
Last night, we saw this amazing dance troupe
made up of street children who had formed
a dance troupe and they performed for the
Prime Minister and myself. And there were
80 different languages and I don't know how
many ethnic groups. And there were like 30
different dances that were being done. And
the Prime Minister was trying to keep up with
-- okay, I think that one is -- (laughter)
-- and they were moving fast. And that diversity
here in Ethiopia is representative of diversity
all throughout Africa. (Applause.) And that's
a strength.
Now, yesterday, I had the privilege to view
Lucy -- you may know Lucy -- she’s our ancestor,
more than 3 million years old. (Applause.)
In this tree of humanity, with all of our
branches and diversity, we all go back to
the same root. We’re all one family -- we're
all one tribe. And yet so much of the suffering
in our world stems from our failure to remember
that -- to not recognize ourselves in each
other. (Applause.)
We think because somebody’s skin is slightly
different, or their hair is slightly different,
or their religious faith is differently expressed,
or they speak a different language that it
justifies somehow us treating them with less
dignity. And that becomes the source of so
many of our problems. And we think somehow
that we make ourselves better by putting other
people down. And that becomes the source of
so many of our problems. When we begin to
see other as somehow less than ourselves -- when
we succumb to these artificial divisions of
faith or sect or tribe or ethnicity -- then
even the most awful abuses are justified in
the minds of those who are thinking in those
ways. And in the end, abusers lose their own
humanity, as well. (Applause.)
Nelson Mandela taught us, “to be free is
not merely to cast off one’s chains, but
to live in a way that respects and enhances
the freedom of others.”
Every one of us is equal. Every one of us
has worth. Every one of us matters. And when
we respect the freedom of others -- no matter
the color of their skin, or how they pray
or who they are or who they love -- we are
all more free. (Applause.) Your dignity depends
on my dignity, and my dignity depends on yours.
Imagine if everyone had that spirit in their
hearts. Imagine if governments operated that
way. (Applause.) Just imagine what the world
could look like -- the future that we could
bequeath these young people.
Yes, in our world, old thinking can be a stubborn
thing. That's one of the reasons why we need
term limits -- old people think old ways.
And you can see my grey hair, I'm getting
old. (Laughter.) The old ways can be stubborn.
But I believe the human heart is stronger.
I believe hearts can change. I believe minds
can open. That’s how change happens. That’s
how societies move forward. It's not always
a straight line -- step by halting step -- sometimes
you go forward, you move back a little bit.
But I believe we are marching, we are pointing
towards ideals of justice and equality.
That’s how your nations won independence
-- not just with rifles, but with principles
and ideals. (Applause.) That's how African
Americans won our civil rights. That's how
South Africans -- black and white -- tore
down apartheid. That's why I can stand before
you today as the first African American President
of the United States. (Applause.)
New thinking. Unleashing growth that creates
opportunity. Promoting development that lifts
all people out of poverty. Supporting democracy
that gives citizens their say. Advancing the
security and justice that delivers peace.
Respecting the human rights of all people.
These are the keys to progress -- not just
in Africa, but around the world. And this
is the work that we can do together.
And I am hopeful. As I prepare to return home,
my thoughts are with that same young man from
Senegal, who said: Here, I have met Africa,
the [Africa] I’ve always believed in. She’s
beautiful and young, full of talent and motivation
and ambition. To which I would simply add,
as you build the Africa you believe in, you
will have no better partner, no better friend
than the United States of America. (Applause.)
God bless Africa. God bless the United States
of America. Thank you very much, everybody.
Thank you. (Applause.)