It is a rare honor in this life to follow
one of your heroes. And John Lewis is one
of my heroes.
Now, I have to imagine that when a younger
John Lewis woke up that morning fifty years
ago and made his way to Brown Chapel, heroics
were not on his mind. A day like this was
not on his mind. Young folks with bedrolls
and backpacks were milling about. Veterans
of the movement trained newcomers in the tactics
of non-violence; the right way to protect
yourself when attacked. A doctor described
what tear gas does to the body, while marchers
scribbled down instructions for contacting
their loved ones. The air was thick with doubt,
anticipation, and fear. They comforted themselves
with the final verse of the final hymn they
sung:
No matter what may be the test, God will take
care of you;
Lean, weary one, upon His breast, God will
take care of you.
Then, his knapsack stocked with an apple,
a toothbrush, a book on government – all
you need for a night behind bars – John
Lewis led them out of the church on a mission
to change America.
President Bush and Mrs. Bush, Governor Bentley,
Members of Congress, Mayor Evans, Reverend
Strong, friends and fellow Americans:
There are places, and moments in America where
this nation’s destiny has been decided.
Many are sites of war – Concord and Lexington,
Appomattox and Gettysburg. Others are sites
that symbolize the daring of America’s character
– Independence Hall and Seneca Falls, Kitty
Hawk and Cape Canaveral.
Selma is such a place.
In one afternoon fifty years ago, so much
of our turbulent history – the stain of
slavery and anguish of civil war; the yoke
of segregation and tyranny of Jim Crow; the
death of four little girls in Birmingham,
and the dream of a Baptist preacher – met
on this bridge.
It was not a clash of armies, but a clash
of wills; a contest to determine the meaning
of America.
And because of men and women like John Lewis,
Joseph Lowery, Hosea Williams, Amelia Boynton,
Diane Nash, Ralph Abernathy, C.T. Vivian,
Andrew Young, Fred Shuttlesworth, Dr. King,
and so many more, the idea of a just America,
a fair America, an inclusive America, a generous
America – that idea ultimately triumphed.
As is true across the landscape of American
history, we cannot examine this moment in
isolation. The march on Selma was part of
a broader campaign that spanned generations;
the leaders that day part of a long line of
heroes.
We gather here to celebrate them. We gather
here to honor the courage of ordinary Americans
willing to endure billy clubs and the chastening
rod; tear gas and the trampling hoof; men
and women who despite the gush of blood and
splintered bone would stay true to their North
Star and keep marching toward justice.
They did as Scripture instructed: “Rejoice
in hope, be patient in tribulation, be constant
in prayer.” And in the days to come, they
went back again and again. When the trumpet
call sounded for more to join, the people
came – black and white, young and old, Christian
and Jew, waving the American flag and singing
the same anthems full of faith and hope. A
white newsman, Bill Plante, who covered the
marches then and who is with us here today,
quipped that the growing number of white people
lowered the quality of the singing. To those
who marched, though, those old gospel songs
must have never sounded so sweet.
In time, their chorus would reach President
Johnson. And he would send them protection,
echoing their call for the nation and the
world to hear:
“We shall overcome.”
What enormous faith these men and women had.
Faith in God – but also faith in America.
The Americans who crossed this bridge were
not physically imposing. But they gave courage
to millions. They held no elected office.
But they led a nation. They marched as Americans
who had endured hundreds of years of brutal
violence, and countless daily indignities
– but they didn’t seek special treatment,
just the equal treatment promised to them
almost a century before.
What they did here will reverberate through
the ages. Not because the change they won
was preordained; not because their victory
was complete; but because they proved that
nonviolent change is possible; that love and
hope can conquer hate.
As we commemorate their achievement, we are
well-served to remember that at the time of
the marches, many in power condemned rather
than praised them. Back then, they were called
Communists, half-breeds, outside agitators,
sexual and moral degenerates, and worse – everything
but the name their parents gave them. Their
faith was questioned. Their lives were threatened.
Their patriotism was challenged.
And yet, what could be more American than
what happened in this place?
What could more profoundly vindicate the idea
of America than plain and humble people – the
unsung, the downtrodden, the dreamers not
of high station, not born to wealth or privilege,
not of one religious tradition but many – coming
together to shape their country’s course?
What greater expression of faith in the American
experiment than this; what greater form of
patriotism is there; than the belief that
America is not yet finished, that we are strong
enough to be self-critical, that each successive
generation can look upon our imperfections
and decide that it is in our power to remake
this nation to more closely align with our
highest ideals?
That’s why Selma is not some outlier in
the American experience. That’s why it’s
not a museum or static monument to behold
from a distance. It is instead the manifestation
of a creed written into our founding documents:
“We the People…in order to form a more
perfect union.”
“We hold these truths to be self-evident,
that all men are created equal.”
These are not just words. They are a living
thing, a call to action, a roadmap for citizenship
and an insistence in the capacity of free
men and women to shape our own destiny. For
founders like Franklin and Jefferson, for
leaders like Lincoln and FDR, the success
of our experiment in self-government rested
on engaging all our citizens in this work.
That’s what we celebrate here in Selma.
That’s what this movement was all about,
one leg in our long journey toward freedom.
The American instinct that led these young
men and women to pick up the torch and cross
this bridge is the same instinct that moved
patriots to choose revolution over tyranny.
It’s the same instinct that drew immigrants
from across oceans and the Rio Grande; the
same instinct that led women to reach for
the ballot and workers to organize against
an unjust status quo; the same instinct that
led us to plant a flag at Iwo Jima and on
the surface of the Moon.
It’s the idea held by generations of citizens
who believed that America is a constant work
in progress; who believed that loving this
country requires more than singing its praises
or avoiding uncomfortable truths. It requires
the occasional disruption, the willingness
to speak out for what’s right and shake
up the status quo.
That’s what makes us unique, and cements
our reputation as a beacon of opportunity.
Young people behind the Iron Curtain would
see Selma and eventually tear down a wall.
Young people in Soweto would hear Bobby Kennedy
talk about ripples of hope and eventually
banish the scourge of apartheid. Young people
in Burma went to prison rather than submit
to military rule. From the streets of Tunis
to the Maidan in Ukraine, this generation
of young people can draw strength from this
place, where the powerless could change the
world’s greatest superpower, and push their
leaders to expand the boundaries of freedom.
They saw that idea made real in Selma, Alabama.
They saw it made real in America.
Because of campaigns like this, a Voting Rights
Act was passed. Political, economic, and social
barriers came down, and the change these men
and women wrought is visible here today in
the presence of African-Americans who run
boardrooms, who sit on the bench, who serve
in elected office from small towns to big
cities; from the Congressional Black Caucus
to the Oval Office.
Because of what they did, the doors of opportunity
swung open not just for African-Americans,
but for every American. Women marched through
those doors. Latinos marched through those
doors. Asian-Americans, gay Americans, and
Americans with disabilities came through those
doors. Their endeavors gave the entire South
the chance to rise again, not by reasserting
the past, but by transcending the past.
What a glorious thing, Dr. King might say.
What a solemn debt we owe.
Which leads us to ask, just how might we repay
that debt?
First and foremost, we have to recognize that
one day’s commemoration, no matter how special,
is not enough. If Selma taught us anything,
it’s that our work is never done – the
American experiment in self-government gives
work and purpose to each generation.
Selma teaches us, too, that action requires
that we shed our cynicism. For when it comes
to the pursuit of justice, we can afford neither
complacency nor despair.
Just this week, I was asked whether I thought
the Department of Justice’s Ferguson report
shows that, with respect to race, little has
changed in this country. I understand the
question, for the report’s narrative was
woefully familiar. It evoked the kind of abuse
and disregard for citizens that spawned the
Civil Rights Movement. But I rejected the
notion that nothing’s changed. What happened
in Ferguson may not be unique, but it’s
no longer endemic, or sanctioned by law and
custom; and before the Civil Rights Movement,
it most surely was.
We do a disservice to the cause of justice
by intimating that bias and discrimination
are immutable, or that racial division is
inherent to America. If you think nothing’s
changed in the past fifty years, ask somebody
who lived through the Selma or Chicago or
L.A. of the Fifties. Ask the female CEO who
once might have been assigned to the secretarial
pool if nothing’s changed. Ask your gay
friend if it’s easier to be out and proud
in America now than it was thirty years ago.
To deny this progress – our progress – would
be to rob us of our own agency; our responsibility
to do what we can to make America better.
Of course, a more common mistake is to suggest
that racism is banished, that the work that
drew men and women to Selma is complete, and
that whatever racial tensions remain are a
consequence of those seeking to play the “race
card” for their own purposes. We don’t
need the Ferguson report to know that’s
not true. We just need to open our eyes, and
ears, and hearts, to know that this nation’s
racial history still casts its long shadow
upon us. We know the march is not yet over,
the race is not yet won, and that reaching
that blessed destination where we are judged
by the content of our character – requires
admitting as much.
“We are capable of bearing a great burden,”
James Baldwin wrote, “once we discover that
the burden is reality and arrive where reality
is.”
This is work for all Americans, and not just
some. Not just whites. Not just blacks. If
we want to honor the courage of those who
marched that day, then all of us are called
to possess their moral imagination. All of
us will need to feel, as they did, the fierce
urgency of now. All of us need to recognize,
as they did, that change depends on our actions,
our attitudes, the things we teach our children.
And if we make such effort, no matter how
hard it may seem, laws can be passed, and
consciences can be stirred, and consensus
can be built.
With such effort, we can make sure our criminal
justice system serves all and not just some.
Together, we can raise the level of mutual
trust that policing is built on – the idea
that police officers are members of the communities
they risk their lives to protect, and citizens
in Ferguson and New York and Cleveland just
want the same thing young people here marched
for – the protection of the law. Together,
we can address unfair sentencing, and overcrowded
prisons, and the stunted circumstances that
rob too many boys of the chance to become
men, and rob the nation of too many men who
could be good dads, and workers, and neighbors.
With effort, we can roll back poverty and
the roadblocks to opportunity. Americans don’t
accept a free ride for anyone, nor do we believe
in equality of outcomes. But we do expect
equal opportunity, and if we really mean it,
if we’re willing to sacrifice for it, then
we can make sure every child gets an education
suitable to this new century, one that expands
imaginations and lifts their sights and gives
them skills. We can make sure every person
willing to work has the dignity of a job,
and a fair wage, and a real voice, and sturdier
rungs on that ladder into the middle class.
And with effort, we can protect the foundation
stone of our democracy for which so many marched
across this bridge – and that is the right
to vote. Right now, in 2015, fifty years after
Selma, there are laws across this country
designed to make it harder for people to vote.
As we speak, more of such laws are being proposed.
Meanwhile, the Voting Rights Act, the culmination
of so much blood and sweat and tears, the
product of so much sacrifice in the face of
wanton violence, stands weakened, its future
subject to partisan rancor.
How can that be? The Voting Rights Act was
one of the crowning achievements of our democracy,
the result of Republican and Democratic effort.
President Reagan signed its renewal when he
was in office. President Bush signed its renewal
when he was in office. One hundred Members
of Congress have come here today to honor
people who were willing to die for the right
it protects. If we want to honor this day,
let these hundred go back to Washington, and
gather four hundred more, and together, pledge
to make it their mission to restore the law
this year.
Of course, our democracy is not the task of
Congress alone, or the courts alone, or the
President alone. If every new voter suppression
law was struck down today, we’d still have
one of the lowest voting rates among free
peoples. Fifty years ago, registering to vote
here in Selma and much of the South meant
guessing the number of jellybeans in a jar
or bubbles on a bar of soap. It meant risking
your dignity, and sometimes, your life. What
is our excuse today for not voting? How do
we so casually discard the right for which
so many fought? How do we so fully give away
our power, our voice, in shaping America’s
future?
Fellow marchers, so much has changed in fifty
years. We’ve endured war, and fashioned
peace. We’ve seen technological wonders
that touch every aspect of our lives, and
take for granted convenience our parents might
scarcely imagine. But what has not changed
is the imperative of citizenship, that willingness
of a 26 year-old deacon, or a Unitarian minister,
or a young mother of five, to decide they
loved this country so much that they’d risk
everything to realize its promise.
That’s what it means to love America. That’s
what it means to believe in America. That’s
what it means when we say America is exceptional.
For we were born of change. We broke the old
aristocracies, declaring ourselves entitled
not by bloodline, but endowed by our Creator
with certain unalienable rights. We secure
our rights and responsibilities through a
system of self-government, of and by and for
the people. That’s why we argue and fight
with so much passion and conviction, because
we know our efforts matter. We know America
is what we make of it.
We are Lewis and Clark and Sacajawea – pioneers
who braved the unfamiliar, followed by a stampede
of farmers and miners, entrepreneurs and hucksters.
That’s our spirit.
We are Sojourner Truth and Fannie Lou Hamer,
women who could do as much as any man and
then some; and we’re Susan B. Anthony, who
shook the system until the law reflected that
truth. That’s our character.
We’re the immigrants who stowed away on
ships to reach these shores, the huddled masses
yearning to breathe free – Holocaust survivors,
Soviet defectors, the Lost Boys of Sudan.
We are the hopeful strivers who cross the
Rio Grande because they want their kids to
know a better life. That’s how we came to
be.
We’re the slaves who built the White House
and the economy of the South. We’re the
ranch hands and cowboys who opened the West,
and countless laborers who laid rail, and
raised skyscrapers, and organized for workers’
rights.
We’re the fresh-faced GIs who fought to
liberate a continent, and we’re the Tuskeegee
Airmen, Navajo code-talkers, and Japanese-Americans
who fought for this country even as their
own liberty had been denied. We’re the firefighters
who rushed into those buildings on 9/11, and
the volunteers who signed up to fight in Afghanistan
and Iraq.
We are the gay Americans whose blood ran on
the streets of San Francisco and New York,
just as blood ran down this bridge.
We are storytellers, writers, poets, and artists
who abhor unfairness, and despise hypocrisy,
and give voice to the voiceless, and tell
truths that need to be told.
We are the inventors of gospel and jazz and
the blues, bluegrass and country, hip-hop
and rock and roll, our very own sounds with
all the sweet sorrow and reckless joy of freedom.
We are Jackie Robinson, enduring scorn and
spiked cleats and pitches coming straight
to his head, and stealing home in the World
Series anyway.
We are the people Langston Hughes wrote of,
who “build our temples for tomorrow, strong
as we know how.”
We are the people Emerson wrote of, “who
for truth and honor’s sake stand fast and
suffer long;” who are “never tired, so
long as we can see far enough.”
That’s what America is. Not stock photos
or airbrushed history or feeble attempts to
define some of us as more American as others.
We respect the past, but we don’t pine for
it. We don’t fear the future; we grab for
it. America is not some fragile thing; we
are large, in the words of Whitman, containing
multitudes. We are boisterous and diverse
and full of energy, perpetually young in spirit.
That’s why someone like John Lewis at the
ripe age of 25 could lead a mighty march.
And that’s what the young people here today
and listening all across the country must
take away from this day. You are America.
Unconstrained by habits and convention. Unencumbered
by what is, and ready to seize what ought
to be. For everywhere in this country, there
are first steps to be taken, and new ground
to cover, and bridges to be crossed. And it
is you, the young and fearless at heart, the
most diverse and educated generation in our
history, who the nation is waiting to follow.
Because Selma shows us that America is not
the project of any one person.
Because the single most powerful word in our
democracy is the word “We.” We The People.
We Shall Overcome. Yes We Can. It is owned
by no one. It belongs to everyone. Oh, what
a glorious task we are given, to continually
try to improve this great nation of ours.
Fifty years from Bloody Sunday, our march
is not yet finished. But we are getting closer.
Two hundred and thirty-nine years after this
nation’s founding, our union is not yet
perfect. But we are getting closer. Our job’s
easier because somebody already got us through
that first mile. Somebody already got us over
that bridge. When it feels the road’s too
hard, when the torch we’ve been passed feels
too heavy, we will remember these early travelers,
and draw strength from their example, and
hold firmly the words of the prophet Isaiah:
“Those who hope in the Lord will renew their
strength. They will soar on wings like eagles.
They will run and not grow weary. They will
walk and not be faint.”
We honor those who walked so we could run.
We must run so our children soar. And we will
not grow weary. For we believe in the power
of an awesome God, and we believe in this
country’s sacred promise.
May He bless those warriors of justice no
longer with us, and bless the United States
of America.