Good morning.
I'm here today to talk
about autonomous, flying beach balls.
No, agile aerial robots like this one.
I'd like to tell you a little bit about the challenges in building these
and some of the terrific opportunities
for applying this technology.
So these robots
are related to unmanned aerial vehicles.
However, the vehicles you see here are big.
They weigh thousands of pounds,
are not by any means agile.
They're not even autonomous.
In fact, many of these vehicles
are operated by flight crews
that can include multiple pilots,
operators of sensors
and mission coordinators.
What we're interested in is developing robots like this --
and here are two other pictures --
of robots that you can buy off the shelf.
So these are helicopters with four rotors
and they're roughly a meter or so in scale
and weigh several pounds.
And so we retrofit these with sensors and processors,
and these robots can fly indoors
without GPS.
The robot I'm holding in my hand
is this one,
and it's been created by two students,
Alex and Daniel.
So this weighs a little more
than a tenth of a pound.
It consumes about 15 watts of power.
And as you can see,
it's about eight inches in diameter.
So let me give you just a very quick tutorial
on how these robots work.
So it has four rotors.
If you spin these rotors at the same speed,
the robot hovers.
If you increase the speed of each of these rotors,
then the robot flies up, it accelerates up.
Of course, if the robot were tilted,
inclined to the horizontal,
then it would accelerate in this direction.
So to get it to tilt, there's one of two ways of doing it.
So in this picture
you see that rotor four is spinning faster
and rotor two is spinning slower.
And when that happens
there's moment that causes this robot to roll.
And the other way around,
if you increase the speed of rotor three
and decrease the speed of rotor one,
then the robot pitches forward.
And then finally,
if you spin opposite pairs of rotors
faster than the other pair,
then the robot yaws about the vertical axis.
So an on-board processor
essentially looks at what motions need to be executed
and combines these motions
and figures out what commands to send to the motors
600 times a second.
That's basically how this thing operates.
So one of the advantages of this design
is, when you scale things down,
the robot naturally becomes agile.
So here R
is the characteristic length of the robot.
It's actually half the diameter.
And there are lots of physical parameters that change
as you reduce R.
The one that's the most important
is the inertia or the resistance to motion.
So it turns out,
the inertia, which governs angular motion,
scales as a fifth power of R.
So the smaller you make R,
the more dramatically the inertia reduces.
So as a result, the angular acceleration,
denoted by Greek letter alpha here,
goes as one over R.
It's inversely proportional to R.
The smaller you make it the more quickly you can turn.
So this should be clear in these videos.
At the bottom right you see a robot
performing a 360 degree flip
in less than half a second.
Multiple flips, a little more time.
So here the processes on board
are getting feedback from accelerometers
and gyros on board
and calculating, like I said before,
commands at 600 times a second
to stabilize this robot.
So on the left, you see Daniel throwing this robot up into the air.
And it shows you how robust the control is.
No matter how you throw it,
the robot recovers and comes back to him.
So why build robots like this?
Well robots like this have many applications.
You can send them inside buildings like this
as first responders to look for intruders,
maybe look for biochemical leaks,
gaseous leaks.
You can also use them
for applications like construction.
So here are robots carrying beams, columns
and assembling cube-like structures.
I'll tell you a little bit more about this.
The robots can be used for transporting cargo.
So one of the problems with these small robots
is their payload carrying capacity.
So you might want to have multiple robots
carry payloads.
This is a picture of a recent experiment we did --
actually not so recent anymore --
in Sendai shortly after the earthquake.
So robots like this could be sent into collapsed buildings
to assess the damage after natural disasters,
or sent into reactor buildings
to map radiation levels.
So one fundamental problem
that the robots have to solve if they're to be autonomous
is essentially figuring out
how to get from point A to point B.
So this gets a little challenging
because the dynamics of this robot are quite complicated.
In fact, they live in a 12-dimensional space.
So we use a little trick.
We take this curved 12-dimensional space
and transform it
into a flat four-dimensional space.
And that four-dimensional space
consists of X, Y, Z and then the yaw angle.
And so what the robot does
is it plans what we call a minimum snap trajectory.
So to remind you of physics,
you have position, derivative, velocity,
then acceleration,
and then comes jerk
and then comes snap.
So this robot minimizes snap.
So what that effectively does
is produces a smooth and graceful motion.
And it does that avoiding obstacles.
So these minimum snap trajectories in this flat space
are then transformed back
into this complicated 12-dimensional space,
which the robot must do
for control and then execution.
So let me show you some examples
of what these minimum snap trajectories look like.
And in the first video,
you'll see the robot going from point A to point B
through an intermediate point.
So the robot is obviously capable
of executing any curve trajectory.
So these are circular trajectories
where the robot pulls about two G's.
Here you have overhead motion capture cameras on the top
that tell the robot where it is 100 times a second.
It also tells the robot where these obstacles are.
And the obstacles can be moving.
And here you'll see Daniel throw this hoop into the air,
while the robot is calculating the position of the hoop
and trying to figure out how to best go through the hoop.
So as an academic,
we're always trained to be able to jump through hoops to raise funding for our labs,
and we get our robots to do that.
(Applause)
So another thing the robot can do
is it remembers pieces of trajectory
that it learns or is pre-programmed.
So here you see the robot
combining a motion
that builds up momentum
and then changes its orientation and then recovers.
So it has to do this because this gap in the window
is only slightly larger than the width of the robot.
So just like a diver stands on a springboard
and then jumps off it to gain momentum,
and then does this pirouette, this two and a half somersault through
and then gracefully recovers,
this robot is basically doing that.
So it knows how to combine little bits and pieces of trajectories
to do these fairly difficult tasks.
So I want change gears.
So one of the disadvantages of these small robots is its size.
And I told you earlier
that we may want to employ lots and lots of robots
to overcome the limitations of size.
So one difficulty
is how do you coordinate lots of these robots?
And so here we looked to nature.
So I want to show you a clip
of Aphaenogaster desert ants
in Professor Stephen Pratt's lab carrying an object.
So this is actually a piece of fig.
Actually you take any object coated with fig juice
and the ants will carry them back to the nest.
So these ants don't have any central coordinator.
They sense their neighbors.
There's no explicit communication.
But because they sense the neighbors
and because they sense the object,
they have implicit coordination across the group.
So this is the kind of coordination
we want our robots to have.
So when we have a robot
which is surrounded by neighbors --
and let's look at robot I and robot J --
what we want the robots to do
is to monitor the separation between them
as they fly in formation.
And then you want to make sure
that this separation is within acceptable levels.
So again the robots monitor this error
and calculate the control commands
100 times a second,
which then translates to the motor commands 600 times a second.
So this also has to be done
in a decentralized way.
Again, if you have lots and lots of robots,
it's impossible to coordinate all this information centrally
fast enough in order for the robots to accomplish the task.
Plus the robots have to base their actions
only on local information,
what they sense from their neighbors.
And then finally,
we insist that the robots be agnostic
to who their neighbors are.
So this is what we call anonymity.
So what I want to show you next
is a video
of 20 of these little robots
flying in formation.
They're monitoring their neighbors' position.
They're maintaining formation.
The formations can change.
They can be planar formations,
they can be three-dimensional formations.
As you can see here,
they collapse from a three-dimensional formation into planar formation.
And to fly through obstacles
they can adapt the formations on the fly.
So again, these robots come really close together.
As you can see in this figure-eight flight,
they come within inches of each other.
And despite the aerodynamic interactions
of these propeller blades,
they're able to maintain stable flight.
(Applause)
So once you know how to fly in formation,
you can actually pick up objects cooperatively.
So this just shows
that we can double, triple, quadruple
the robot strength
by just getting them to team with neighbors, as you can see here.
One of the disadvantages of doing that
is, as you scale things up --
so if you have lots of robots carrying the same thing,
you're essentially effectively increasing the inertia,
and therefore you pay a price; they're not as agile.
But you do gain in terms of payload carrying capacity.
Another application I want to show you --
again, this is in our lab.
This is work done by Quentin Lindsey who's a graduate student.
So his algorithm essentially tells these robots
how to autonomously build
cubic structures
from truss-like elements.
So his algorithm tells the robot
what part to pick up,
when and where to place it.
So in this video you see --
and it's sped up 10, 14 times --
you see three different structures being built by these robots.
And again, everything is autonomous,
and all Quentin has to do
is to get them a blueprint
of the design that he wants to build.
So all these experiments you've seen thus far,
all these demonstrations,
have been done with the help of motion capture systems.
So what happens when you leave your lab
and you go outside into the real world?
And what if there's no GPS?
So this robot
is actually equipped with a camera
and a laser rangefinder, laser scanner.
And it uses these sensors
to build a map of the environment.
What that map consists of are features --
like doorways, windows,
people, furniture --
and it then figures out where its position is
with respect to the features.
So there is no global coordinate system.
The coordinate system is defined based on the robot,
where it is and what it's looking at.
And it navigates with respect to those features.
So I want to show you a clip
of algorithms developed by Frank Shen
and Professor Nathan Michael
that shows this robot entering a building for the very first time
and creating this map on the fly.
So the robot then figures out what the features are.
It builds the map.
It figures out where it is with respect to the features
and then estimates its position
100 times a second
allowing us to use the control algorithms
that I described to you earlier.
So this robot is actually being commanded
remotely by Frank.
But the robot can also figure out
where to go on its own.
So suppose I were to send this into a building
and I had no idea what this building looked like,
I can ask this robot to go in,
create a map
and then come back and tell me what the building looks like.
So here, the robot is not only solving the problem,
how to go from point A to point B in this map,
but it's figuring out
what the best point B is at every time.
So essentially it knows where to go
to look for places that have the least information.
And that's how it populates this map.
So I want to leave you
with one last application.
And there are many applications of this technology.
I'm a professor, and we're passionate about education.
Robots like this can really change the way
we do K through 12 education.
But we're in Southern California,
close to Los Angeles,
so I have to conclude
with something focused on entertainment.
I want to conclude with a music video.
I want to introduce the creators, Alex and Daniel,
who created this video.
(Applause)
So before I play this video,
I want to tell you that they created it in the last three days
after getting a call from Chris.
And the robots that play the video
are completely autonomous.
You will see nine robots play six different instruments.
And of course, it's made exclusively for TED 2012.
Let's watch.
(Music)
(Applause)